Guide to the Middlesex County Archaeological Digs and Course Records, 1976 - 1983
Middlesex County Archaeological Digs and Course Records, 1976 - 1983
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)
2000-27
2.5
4
In the spring of 1974, Professor Stephen Dyson of the Wesleyan University Classics Department took his Introduction to Archaeology Class on a preliminary excavation in Middlefield, Connecticut. This was a test to see if there was potential for an archaeology class based on fieldwork. Since the success at the first excavation, Wesleyan has continued to take its students on excavations within Middlesex County, Connecticut.
The Middlesex County Archaeological Digs and Course Records were compiled by Stephen Dyson documenting his archaeology labs conducted in the field and courses focusing on local sites. It includes student essays, student field sheets, student lab inventories, grant proposals, Connecticut Historical Commission Inventory sheets for sites in the Middlesex area, and photos of mid-19th century topographic and housing maps of Middletown, Middlefield, and Cromwell.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Transferred from Doug Charles, Anthropology/Archaeology Program/Museum Coordinator, in June 2000.
Historical Note
In spring 1974, Professor Stephen Dyson of the Classics Department took his Introduction to Archaeology Class on a preliminary excavation in Lyman Orchards in Middlefield, Connecticut. This was a test to see if there was potential for an archaeology class based on fieldwork. The excavation was successful and archaeology classes continued to visit sites in Connecticut, particularly within Middlesex County.
The first time Wesleyan did a European excavation was in 1969 when it joined with Brown University in Buccino, Italy to excavate Roman villas. Later, in 1974, Dyson took a group of students to the town of Cosa, Italy for a dig. In 1982, Professor Stephen White of history and medieval studies and Clark Maines of art history coordinated with Dyson to take a Wesleyan crew to Soissons in France to study the Augustinian abbey of Saint-Jean-des-Vignes. These trips occurred during the summer and often times they would return for several consecutive summers.
As of 2008, the archaeology program continues conduct excavation labs within Middlesex county.
Collection Overview
This Middlesex County Archaeological Digs Records were compiled by Stephen Dyson. They document his archaeology labs conducted in the field and courses focusing on local Connecticut sites. It includes student essays, student field sheets, student lab inventories, grant proposals, Connecticut Historical Commission Inventory sheets for sites in the Middlesex area, and photos of mid-19th century topographic and housing maps of the towns of Middletown, Middlefield, and Cromwell, Connecticut.
There is a 1977 report written by Stephen Dyson (Box 1, Folder 10) which reviews the findings and the importance of the class after their first three years. He wrote about the Magill House, their second site of excavation, and the conclusions that were made about the wealthy Captain Magill of the 19th century. After their third excavation at Kelly's Pet Store, formerly known as Doc Hall's House, he was able to compare the different life styles of the two families. The Hall House residents lived a more reserved life and preferred the pipe over drink. The class concluded that the Magill House was full of luxuries through analysis of pottery found during the excavation. Dyson wrote that, with the success of his class excavating the Middlesex County area, it would soon include the community and start a program with children from the community.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Dyson, Stephen L.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Faculty.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.; Archaeology--Connecticut.; Excavations (Archaeology)--Connecticut.; Archaeology--Study and teaching--United States.; Archaeology--Research--United States.; Middlesex County (Conn.)--History.; Middletown (Conn.)--History.; Cromwell (Conn.)--History.; Middlefield (Conn.: Town)--History.; Photographs.; Connecticut Historical Commission.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Materials from Class Digs
  - Contract Maps (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cromwell- Contract (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Haddam Survey (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Middletown - Probate Xeroxes (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Northford - Warham Williams House (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Norwalk - Contract (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Class Forms (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photos (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Student Papers (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1977 Evaluation by Stephen Dyson and Supplementary Information (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Danforth - Field Sheets, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hall House - Field Sheets, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hall House - Lab Inventories, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Magill House - Pottery (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Metro South - Field Sheets, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - South Mayd - Field Sheets, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - South Mayd - Site Drawings, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Summer Street - Field Sheets, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - White Eagle Café
    - Contract (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Field Sheets (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Lab Inventory (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Vessel Inventory Sheets, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Connecticut Historical Commission Survey
  - Phase I & II Grant Application (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Accounting - Wesleyan Survey, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence Sent (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence Received (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Final Report (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1978 Cromwell Inventory Forms (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1978 East Hampton Inventory Forms (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1978 Haddam Inventory Forms (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1978 Middletown/Middlefield Inventory Forms (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1978 Portland Inventory Forms (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Oversize materials
  - Photographic reproductions of mid-19th century topographic and housing maps of Middletown, Middlefield, and Cromwell (Box 4)